A Guide to the Frederick (Fritz) Earnest Nolting, Jr. Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #12804
Frederick (Fritz) Earnest Nolting, Jr. Papers 1890-1989
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
12804
ca. 12,000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection wasa gift from Mrs. Frederick Nolting.
Biographical Sketch
Educator, diplomat and banker, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr. was born August 24, 1911 in Richmond, Virginia to Frederick Earnest Nolting, Sr. and Mary Buford Nolting. Known as "Fritz," he spent his early childhood and student years in Richmond attending the St. Christopher's School. Later as an undergraduate he attended the University of Virginia in Charlottesville where he earned a B.A. degree in history and went on to work as an investment banker in the family business in Richmond for the next five years.
In 1939, Nolting returned to graduate studies at the University of Virginia, earning an M. A. (1940) and a Ph.D.(1942) in philosophy and serving as a lecturing fellow in that field. He also earned a second M.A. in philosophy at Harvard in 1941. During World War II, Nolting served overseas in the Navy, achieving the rank of Lieutenant Commander. In 1946, he left the Navy and began a career that would span 18 years with the Department of State. His service included assignments as a member of the U.S. Delegation to the United Nations (1951); as Special Assistant to Secretaries of State Dean Acheson and John Foster Dulles for Mutual Security Affairs (1953-1955) and as Alternate U.S. Representative to the North Atlantic Council (NATO) in Paris (1955-1961). In 1961, President Kennedy named Nolting as Ambassador to the Republic of South Vietnam where he served until 1963 in what was to be a period of shifting U.S.Vietnamese policy developments that precipitated the overthrow and assassination of President Ngo Dinh Diem.
In 1964, Nolting retired from the U.S. Government to become Vice-President in charge of the European offices of the Morgan Guaranty Trust Company in Paris (1964-1969), then Assistant to the Chairman in New York City (1969-1973) and, finally, as consultant to the company (1973-1976).
During this time, Nolting had returned to the University of Virginia to serve as Diplomat-in-Residence (1971-1973) before going on to hold teaching and administrative posts as Olsson Professor of Business Administration in the Darden School of Business (1973-1976), Professor in the Woodrow Wilson Department of Government and Foreign Affairs and Director of the Miller Center of Public Affairs. He also served as Chairman of the Board of Trustees of the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation and as a member of the Center for Advanced Studies and the International Management and Development Institute.
In 1982, Nolting retired from the University of Virginia and devoted a good deal of his time to the writing of his book, From trust to tragedy: the political memoirs of Frederick Nolting, Kennedy's ambassador to Diem's Vietnam, which he published in 1988. The book serves as Nolting's personal testament to his role as U.S. Ambassador in Saigon and as a critical analysis of the conflicting political strategies that existed among the many policy making players during that volatile period of the U.S. involvement in Vietnam.
On December 14, 1989, at age 78, Nolting died and was survived by his wife, Olivia Lindsay Crumpler whom he had married in 1940 and who is presently residing in Charlottesville and by their four daughters: Mary Nolting Bruner and Jane Nolting Meniktos both of Charlottesville; Grace Lindsay Nolting of Columbia, Virginia and Frances Temple of Geneva, New York.
Scope and Content
The collection contains ca. 12,000 items (17 shelf feet) and consists of a large quantity of generally routine personal and official correspondence; a smaller portion of "Selected Correspondence" listed by correspondent name; professional papers associated with Nolting's governmental, business and academic career activities; personal papers containing military and property records; manuscript notes, drafts and correspondence relating to Nolting's publications and an assortment of photographs (ca. 500 items), many of which were take during his service in Vietnam.
Interesting documents within the collection groupings include: (a) Correspondence: The exchange of letters with Dean Rusk, W. Averell Harriman and the editors of the New York Times in which Nolting challenges some of the U.S. policy strategies of the 1961-1963 Vietnam experience. (b) Professional Papers: Copies of State Department declassified documents that reveal the unfolding day-to-day actions that led to a major shift in U.S. relations with the South Vietnamese Government and that resulted in the overthrow and death of President Diem. (c) Personal Papers: Records of the Nolting family involvement in the restoration and preservation of the historic Sully and Chantilly properties in Virginia. (d) Photographs: Dramatic photographs of some of the major players involved in the U.S.-Vietnam policy drama of 1961-1964, including: President Diem, Henry Cabot Lodge, W. Averell Harriman, Maxwell Taylor, Vice-President Johnson and Ambassador Nolting.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1936-1959; (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1962; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964; (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966; (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969; (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1970; (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972; (6 folders) (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1975; (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1978; (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1981; (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1989, n.d.; (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - Selected Correspondence--Abramson, Rudy, 1984 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Acheson, Dean, 1959-1962 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Baldwin, Charles F., 1962 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Bice, Raymond C., 1975-1978 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Bradley, Omar N., 1953 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Byrd, Harry F., Jr., 1962-1978 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Carter, Hodding, III, 1978-1979 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Casteen, John T., III, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Coffman, Suzanne E., 1985, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Colby, William E., 1973-1988 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Dabney, Virginius, 1945-1975 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Darden, Colgate W., Jr., 1977-1978 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Durbrow, Elbridge, 1961-1962 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Dulles, John Foster, 1953-1958 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence--Editor, New York Times, 1961-1973, n.d. (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1955-1958 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Felt, Harry D., 1964-1967 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1961-1972 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Gilpatric, Roswell L., 1979 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Hagan, Joseph Addison, 1965-1977 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Harkins, Paul D., 1964-1971 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Harriman, W. Averell, 1961-1963 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Hereford, Frank L, Jr., 1975-1977 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Higgins, Marguerite, 1965 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Hill, Ivan, 1974-1978 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Johnson, Lyndon B., 1963-1964 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence--Johnson, Mrs. Lyndon B., 1974 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Johnson, U. Alexis, 1961-1965 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Kennedy, John F., 1963 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Kennedy, Robert F., 1967 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Kissinger, Henry A., 1975 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Lansdale, Edward G., 1965 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Lippmann, Walter, 1958 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Lemnitzer, L. L., 1960-1962 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Loving, Boyce, 1952-1953 (Box 12)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Malone, Dumas, 1973 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- McBride, Robert H., 1976 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- McCarthy, Frank, 1974-1977 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- McNamara, Robert S., 1962-1964 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Murrow, Edward R., 1964 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Ngo Dinh Diem, 1961 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Ngo Dinh Nhu (Madame Nhu), 1964-1966 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Nguyen Dinh Thuan, 1963-1978, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Nixon, Richard M., 1968-1973 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence--Nolting (Family Correspondence), 1944-1963 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Ramazani, Ronhollah K., 1977 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Riddle, Sturgis L., 1969 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Rockefeller, John D., III, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Rusk, Dean, 1960-1975 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Russell, Bertrand, 1941 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Sands, Oliver Jackson, Jr., 1965-1966 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Schiff, E. L. C., 1976-1978 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Shannon, David A., 1971-1977 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Shannon, Edgar F., Jr., 1971-1977 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Spellman, Francis Cardinal, 1964-1966 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Stassen, Harold E., 1955 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Steiner, George A., 1975-1976 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Stettinius, Edward R., Jr., 1945 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Taylor, Maxwell D., 1962-1978 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Trueheart, William C., 1960-1963 (Box 13)
  - Selected Correspondence-- Williams, Murat W., 1961-1978 (Box 13)
- Series II: Professional Papers
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company --Aerospace Industries Association, 1970-1973 (Box 14)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Agency for International Development, 1971-1972 (Box 14)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Barque Du Congo, 1969-1971 (Box 14)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Board of Trustees of Foreign Parishes, 1969-1973 (Box 14)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--British North American Committee, 1969-1972; (1-3 of 5 folders) (Box 14)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--British North American Committee, 1969-1972; (4-5 of 5 folders) (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Club Memberships, 1967-1971 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--European and Political Development Conference, London, 1972 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--European Enterprises Development Company, 1969-1970 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--France-America Society, 1969-1971 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--German-American Industrialists Meeting (Dec 7- 8), 1970 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--IMF/IBRD Meetings (World Bank and Fund), 1971-1972 (Box 15)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--International Banking Division, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--International Council, 1969-1971 (Box 16)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--International Finance Corporation and World Bank, 1970-1972 (Box 16)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Miscellaneous Office Records, 1964-1977, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--National Strategy Information Center, 1971-1973; (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Overseas Development Council, 1969-1972 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Overseas Private Investment Corporation, 1969-1971 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Smith Barney Seminar, 1971 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Special Reports and Press Releases, 1969-1972 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Trade Bill, 1969-1972 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Trade with China, 1971 (Box 17)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Tunisia (American Committee for Assistance), 1969-1970 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--United Nations, 1968-1970 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--U.S. Government Accounts, 1969-1971 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--U.S. Postal Service, 1971 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--U.S. Treasury Department, 1969-1972 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Washington Contacts, 1970 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--Washington Office, 1969-1971 (Box 18)
  - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company--World Trade Institute, 1971-1972 (Box 18)
  - University of Virginia --Center for Advanced Studies, 1973-1978 (Box 19)
  - University of Virginia--Central Atlantic Environment Center, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
  - University of Virginia--Ethics Seminar, 1977-1981; (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - University of Virginia--Honor Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--International Management and Development Institute, 1972-1976; (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Legislative Veto Conference (Feb 10-11), 1978 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Miscellaneous, 1973-1980, n.d. (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Queen Elizabeth Visit to Monticello, 1976 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Randolph-Macon College, 1973-1980 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Society of Fellows, 1976-1983, n.d. (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Taft Institute, 1975-1976 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1975-1981 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--University Press of Virginia, 1985-1987 (Box 20)
  - University of Virginia--University Communications and Notices, 1973-1982, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - University of Virginia--U.S.-China Trade Symposium (Sep 24-25), 1976 (Box 21)
  - University of Virginia--Virginia Foundation for the Humanities, 1974-1977 (Box 21)
  - University of Virginia--Who's Who in America, 1976 (Box 21)
  - U.S. Department of State--Atlantic Council, 1968-1981; (4 Folders) (Box 22)
  - U.S. Department of State--Issue Background Releases, 1949-1955 (Box 22)
  - U.S. Department of State--Foreign Service Personnel Records, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1945-1964; (4 folders) (Box 23)
  - U.S. Department of State--Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1980, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - U.S. Department of State--Oral History Drafts and Related Correspondence, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1966-1988, n.d.; (4 folders) (Box 24)
  - U.S. Department of State--Speech Material, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1951-1982, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 25)
  - U.S. Department of State--State Department Documents and Communications, Vietnam, 1963-1982, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box 26)
  - U.S. Department of State--Historical Background Records, Vietnam, 1956-1988, n.d.; (1-2 of 10 folders) (Box 26)
  - U.S. Department of State--Historical Background Records, Vietnam, 1956-1988, n.d.; (3-6 of 10 folders) (Box 27)
  - U.S. Department of State--Historical Background Records, Vietnam, 1956-1988, n.d.; (7-10 of 10 folders) (Box 28)
- Series III: Personal Papers
  - Military Service Records and World War II Journals, 1943-1960; (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1978 (Box 30)
  - Real Property Records, 1946-1983, n.d.; (1-2 of 12 folders) (Box 30)
  - Real Property Records, 1946-1983, n.d.; (3-12 of 12 folders) (Box 31)
  - Scholastic Class Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1939-1942; (1-5 of 10 folders) (Box 32)
  - Scholastic Class Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1939-1942; (6-10 of 10 folders) (Box 33)
  - Wills, Certificates and Passports, Nolting Family, 1940-1987, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box 34)
- Series IV: Publications
  - Magazine Articles, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1971-1974 (Box 35)
  - Manuscript Drafts and Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1978-1987; (1-3 of 17 folders) (Box 35)
  - Manuscript Drafts and Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1978-1987; (4-7 of 17 folders) (Box 36)
  - Manuscript Drafts and Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1978-1987; (8-13 of 17 folders) (Box 37)
  - Manuscript Drafts and Notes, Frederick Earnest Nolting, Jr., 1978-1987; (14-17 of 17 folders) (Box 38)
  - Reviews and Monograph: From trust to tragedy: the political memoirs of Frederick Nolting, Kennedy's ambassador to Diem's Vietnam, 1988-1989 (Box 38)
- Series V: Photographs
  - Ambassadorial Period, Vietnam, 1960's; (7 folders) (Box 39)
  - Miscellaneous (Family), 1890-1975, n.d. (Box 39)